The new Duskmon set is bringing with it
five new mechanics to the game as well
as some old favorites. So, let's go over
everything you need to know about them.
The first new mechanic is the new
enchantment subtype, rooms. Rooms are an
interesting mix of split cards and
classes. Room cards are split into two
halves. Each half is called a door. And
when you go to cast this spell, you pick
a door and pay that door's costs. the
door becomes unlocked and you get that
room's abilities. You may then at some
point later pay the cost of the other
door as a sorcery and completely unlocks
the room. This is a special action
similar to playing a land or paying a
morph cost and does not use the stack
and cannot be responded to. It has been
confirmed, although at the time of
recording we don't have any previews,
that some rooms will have triggered
abilities that trigger when you unlock
this door. There are also cards that
care about fully unlocking rooms, too.
Now, there are a couple of special rules
to keep in mind for rooms. When they're
on the battlefield, a room has the
characteristics of its currently
unlocked doors. So, if you had doll
maker shop unlocked, you could destroy
it with abrupt decay. However, as soon
as the other door is unlocked, the room
would have a converted mana value of
eight. On this point, while in your
library hand, and graveyard, the room
has the combined mana value of both
halves, as well as having both of its
names. So, you wouldn't be able to use
Sun Titan's ability to bring it back
from the graveyard. However, while on
the stack, it will only have the mana
value of the half you're casting.
Another thing to note is that while in
play, if both doors are unlocked, the
card will have two names, too.
Interestingly, if a room enters the
battlefield without you paying any of
its costs, both doors will be considered
locked and none of its abilities will be
active. It will also have no mana value
while in play. You can then of course
pay the cards door cost to unlock the
rooms just like normal. Next we have
manifest dread. A new twist on the
manifest mechanic. To manifest dread,
you get to look at the top two cards of
your library, then put one in the
graveyard and put the other face down on
the battlefield as a colorless two two
with no name, mana cost, or creature
type. And just like the original
manifest mechanic, you can turn that
card face up as a special action at any
time as long as it's a creature by
paying its mana cost. Every seasoned
player knows that putting cards into the
graveyard is never a bad thing, and
being able to choose which card goes
where is an excellent buff. Don't
forget, there's plenty of faceown
synergies in the previously released
set, Murders at Carlo of Mana. A couple
of other rules to remember with faceown
cards. You can't mix them up with other
faceown cards. They always must be
easily differentiated from one another.
If one of the manifested creatures has
the morph ability, you can pay that cost
instead to turn it face up. A neat trick
to remember, if you blink a face down
creature, they'll return to the
battlefield face up. However, any
non-permanent cards will remain exiled.
And don't forget, at the end of the
game, you must reveal any face down
permanence to show your opponent they
were put face down legally. Next, we
have survival, a triggered ability that
triggers at the beginning of your second
main phase if the creature is tapped.
All the creatures in the Duskorn set
with the survivor creature type will
have this ability. Keep in mind this
ability doesn't care how the creature
becomes tapped, just that it is so by
the beginning of the second main phase.
So you can simply attack with the
creature or perhaps use something like
convoke and tap the creature that way.
Any mechanic that gives a bonus via
things you would normally be doing is
always something to keep an eye on.
One rule thing to note, if the creature
becomes untapped while the survival
trigger is on the stack, the ability
won't do anything.
Moving on to another simple mechanic
that rewards you for simply playing the
game. Eerie. Eerie is a triggered
ability that triggers whenever an
enchantment you control enters the
battlefield or whenever you fully unlock
a room. Again, another mechanic to keep
a close eye on as this is extremely easy
to trigger. We also got Valavoth's
layer, which is an enchantment land. So,
this will trigger Eerie, too. Onto the
last new mechanic of the set, we have
impending, and this is my favorite of
the lot. Impending is a mechanic that is
appearing on the cycle of overlords, one
for each color. As an alternative
casting cost, you can cast the Overlord
for its impending cost. The Overlord
will enter with a number of time
counters equal to the number next to
impending. For as long as it has a time
counter on it, it isn't a creature. At
the beginning of your end step, you
remove a time counter from it. Just to
make things perfectly clear, if you cast
the overlords for their impending cost,
you will get the enters triggered
ability. And of course, your overlord
will be completely immune to creature
removal or creature board wipes, with
the downside being that it can't attack
or block. Once that last time counter is
removed, it's back to being a creature
again. And don't forget, just like with
manifest, if you blink an impending
creature, it will re-enter the
battlefield with no time counters on it.
This is also true for any of the
enduring cards that have died and come
back as an enchantment. blink them to
return them to their creature selves.
So, you might want to pick up a couple
of copies of scroll shift. One of the
first returning mechanics we have is
delirium, which cares about if you have
four or more card types in your
graveyard. We can see this mechanic on
winter nisanthropic guide. As long as
you have delirium, each opponent has
their hand side reduced to seven minus
the amount of card types you have in
your graveyard. Here is the easiest way
to remember all card types. Pickle abs,
planaines walker, instant, creature,
kindred, land, enchantment, artifact,
battle, sorcery.
How long is that acronym going to last?
One returning mechanic that is nice to
get a proper full cycle of again, the
lay lines. Lay lines are four mana
enchantments that you can play at the
start of the game for free if they're in
your opening hand. So after each player
has decided to keep their hands but
before the starting players untap step
you can put any lay lines in your hand
onto the battlefield. If MTG history has
told us anything it's well worth keeping
an eye on this cycle too. And our last
returning mechanic which I did not
expect to see at all is njutsu as seen
on the planaineswalker for the set. Kao
bane of nightmares. Njutsu lets you
return an unblocked creature to your
hand and put the Njutsu card in its
place, tapped and attacking for a cost.
You generally want to pair njutsu with
cards that have built-in evasion, like
flying or creatures that simply can't be
blocked. The most obvious time to
activate njutsu is after your opponent
has declared their blocks. But there are
two other ways you can use it. If your
opponent goes to remove one of your
creatures after the declare blocker
step, you can simply njutsu them away
and let the removal spell fizzle. And
finally, perhaps one of the lesserk
known times, you can still njutsu a
creature after combat damage has been
dealt. After the combat damage step,
where damage has been dealt, there is an
end of combat step. This is where at the
end of combat triggers will trigger. But
one important thing to remember is
during this step, creatures are still in
combat. They're still attacking and
they're still blocking. So you can still
njutsu a creature into play if you want.
So that is every mechanic coming to
Duskorn. What do you think? Let me know
what mechanic you're looking forward to
the most. As always, if you learned
something, be sure to like the video and
subscribe because if you don't,